<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>Alexandre Touret's Blog</title><link>http://blog.touret.info/en/</link><description>Architecte logiciel, développeur, bidouilleur (dans le désordre)</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 08:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://blog.touret.info/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Enhancing Asynchronous Transaction Monitoring: Implementing Distributed Tracing in Apache Camel Applications with OpenTelemetry</title><link>http://blog.touret.info/en/2023/09/05/distributed-tracing-opentelemetry-camel-artemis/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author><name>Alexandre Touret</name></author><guid>http://blog.touret.info/en/2023/09/05/distributed-tracing-opentelemetry-camel-artemis/</guid><description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/assets/images/2023/09/nick-fewings-4dI5OP2Ee64-unsplash.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div>Picture Credit: Nick FEWINGS IntroductionIn today&rsquo;s dynamic landscape, Distributed Tracing has emerged as an indispensable practice. It helps to understand what is under the hood of distributed transactions, providing answers to pivotal questions: What comprises these diverse requests? What contextual information accompanies them? How extensive is their duration?
Since the introduction of Google&rsquo;s Dapper, a plethora of tracing solutions has flooded the scene. Among them, OpenTelemetry has risen as the frontrunner.]]></description></item><item><title>Moving on to Fish shell (and beyond)</title><link>http://blog.touret.info/en/2023/07/21/fish-shell/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Jul 2023 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author><name>Alexandre Touret</name></author><guid>http://blog.touret.info/en/2023/07/21/fish-shell/</guid><description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/assets/images/2023/07/jakub-kapusnak-vLQzopDRSNI-unsplash.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div>While chatting with one of my WL colleague, I stumbled upon Fish shell. I immediately liked its autocompletion and extensibility mechanisms. After many years using BASH and ZSH, I therefore decided to move on to this new shell.
Unlike the others, it&rsquo;s not POSIX-compatible.
Furthermore, to get (at least) the same functionalities as OhMyZsh, I chose to install StarShip.
I will then describe how I moved on and updated my existing tools such as SdkMan.]]></description></item><item><title>Real life Rest API Versioning for dummies</title><link>http://blog.touret.info/en/2023/03/27/rest-api-versioning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Mar 2023 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author><name>Alexandre Touret</name></author><guid>http://blog.touret.info/en/2023/03/27/rest-api-versioning/</guid><description><![CDATA[<div class="featured-image">
                <img src="/assets/images/2023/03/vardan-papikyan-DnXqvmS0eXM-unsplash.webp" referrerpolicy="no-referrer">
            </div>Once upon a time an API &hellip; Second Law of Consulting “No matter how it looks at first, it’s always a people problem” - Gerald M. Weinberg Once upon a time, the ACME Corporation was building a brand new IT product. It aimed at a new software to manage bookstores through a web interface and an API.
In the first steps, the developers drew up a first roadmap of their API based on the expectations of their first customers.]]></description></item></channel></rss>